Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series V. Campaign for U.S. Congress
1966
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson)
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.05
5 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh made his first run for public office as a Republican candidate for U.S. Congress from Pittsburgh's heavily Democratic Fourteenth Congressional District. Despite hard work and solid research, Thornburgh lost to Democrat incumbent, William Moorhead. The documentation of this campaign is detailed and colorful and represents an earnest, issue oriented campaign from the pre TV/polling era. These files are in nine sections: Campaign Plans and Ephemera; Issues and Position Papers; Opposition Research; News Releases and Media; Campaign Volunteer Effort; Candidate Thornburgh's Files; Election Results; Campaign Finances; and Correspondence. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Government; Politics; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Political activists -- Pennsylvania; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; United States. Congress. House -- Elections; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Moorhead, William S. (William Singer); Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick
- Campaign for United States Congress, 1966; V.
  Scope and Contents note
  "Because of the depleted state of the local party and my persistent inquisitiveness about how to improve the community and help solve its problems, party official approached me to run for mayor of Pittsburgh. And although I begged off at that time, I was nevertheless hooked on politics and did succumb to the 1966 congressional campaign" ("From Star Car to the Governor's Office," JFK School Bulletin, Fall, Winter, 1987).
  And so it was in 1966, Thornburgh made his first run for public office as a Republican candidate for U.S. Congress from Pittsburgh's Fourteenth Congressional District, wholly contained within the City of Pittsburgh, and where Democrat registered voters outnumbered Republicans by over 3:1. Thornburgh faced running against William S. Moorhead, Jr., who was the four-year Democrat incumbent who had won election easily twice before. As stated in his book, "Ginny and I had no particular issues on which to challenge Moorhead and no illusions about our ability to win the seat. We knew, however, that we had to test our interest in running for public office" (Evidence, p. 25).
  This was a lonely endeavor at the start when news of Thornburgh for Congress, delivered to Pittsburgh's two newspapers, the Post Gazette and Press, merited small mentions, in one case not even mentioning Thornburgh's name in the headline: "Lawyer Seeking Moorhead Seat." Most of spring of 1966 was spent attending various Republican ward meetings and soliciting endorsements. On Primary Day, May 17, Thornburgh, in what he describes as a "smashing victory," corralled 78% of the meager Republican turnout, but as he further states "the greater challenge lay ahead" ("Evidence" draft, p. 106).
  By Primary Day the campaign, now chaired by John Heinz, had come together quite well. Finances were handled smoothly and a group of volunteer supporters provided a strong research team. Briefing books were prepared on issues of importance, and ultimately a compendium of positions was put together including topics such as: hard line against organized crime and official corruption, concern for the elderly, urban problems, strong civil rights position, support for United Nations, conservative fiscal policies, transportation issues, job training, improved public education, and concern about Vietnam. It is notable that many, even most, of these topics of concern in 1966 recurred in Thornburgh's continued career and are well documented in the archives.
  The General Election campaign included attending a three-day candidates' conference sponsored by the Republican Congressional Campaign Committee in Washington. Of interest is that another "rookie" challenging a Democrat incumbent and attending this conference was President George H.W. Bush. The fall was busy with events and campaign appearances. Travel around the district was by what became known at the "Star Car," a clunker Rambler station wagon. There were three debates between Moorhead and Thornburgh, and Ginny Thornburgh energetically master-minded a dedicated volunteer organization. These were the times of door-to-door canvassing of voters, handing out emery boards and calorie counters with "Thornburgh for Congress," and billboards picturing Thornburgh holding a large wooden spoon entitled "Thornburgh Will Stir Things Up in Congress."
  Despite all the hard work, solid research, and dedicated volunteer activity, ultimately Thornburgh lost to William Moorhead on Election Day, 82,732 to 38,528. As Thornburgh concludes in his book: "All, of course, was not for naught. Ginny and I discovered how much we actually enjoyed the campaign process - meeting and mingling with the voters, puzzling through our positions on difficult issues, and feeling that there was indeed a way to make a difference for the better in people's lives" (Evidence, p. 30). Even the Post Gazette noted "In Mr. Thornburgh the GOP has presented an exceptionally attractive candidate of the sort who should be encouraged to run for public office. While he did not pick the right office at the right time, we hope he will be encouraged to stay active in politics so that the public can avail itself of his services on another occasion" ("Evidence" draft, p. l14).
  Researchers should take note that issue background material here relates and interconnects with other Pittsburgh and Allegheny County reports and articles in these other sections of the archive: "Civic Activities," "Politics," and "Constitutional Convention." These campaign archives are organized in nine sections: "Campaign Plans and Ephemera," "Issues and Position Papers," "Opposition Research," "News Releases and Media," "Campaign Volunteer Effort," "Candidate Thornburgh's Files," "Election Results," "Campaign Finances," and "Correspondence."
  - Campaign Plans and Ephemera, 1.
    These files are arranged in five sections: GOP candidate information, campaign plans, campaign headquarters, Thornburgh for Congress, and campaign mailings. The "GOP candidate files" include materials on the '66 Democrat candidates, supplied by the Republican National Committee. "Campaign plans" include information gathered on voters, polling places and congressional districts. "Campaign headquarters" provides information on the headquarters opening, includes campaign correspondence and even the flower covered guest registry. "Thornburgh for Congress" includes materials that relate to the campaign kick-off and progression, as well as campaign ephemera. "Campaign mailings" consist of correspondence and mailings to and from the Thornburgh campaign headquarters.
    - GOP Candidate Information
      - Republican National Committee Candidates Information, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Republican National Committee Fact Book 1966 Election Campaign (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - 1966 Candidates Conference, June 29, 1966 - July 12, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Campaign Plans
      - Fourteenth Congressional District of Pennsylvania, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Campaign References (published reports) (annotated), 1966 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Allegheny County GOP and Voter Data, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Campaign Binder: County Analysis, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Fourteenth Congressional District: Analysis and Statistics, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Polling Places, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Campaign Headquarters
      - Open House, June 13, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - Opening, September 12, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - Guest Registry, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Thornburgh for Congress
      - Thornburgh for Congress Announcement, February 1966 (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Thornburgh's Biography, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - Thornburgh for Congress Committee, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Fourteenth Congressional District Campaign Kick-off Rally, April 13, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 17)
      - Endorsements of Thornburgh for Congress, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 18)
      - Schedules, Invitations and Event Material, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 19)
      - Editorial, Fall, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 20)
      - Thornburgh address for Republican Nomination for U.S. Congress in the 14th Congressional District, April 13, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Campaign Political Binder [New Material Added], 1966
      - Early campaign plans, January-February 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 41)
      - Campaign Expense Plan, January 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 42)
      - Campaign in Progress, January-October 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 43)
      - Volunteer canvasing, September 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 44)
      - American Institute for Research Plans, March-May 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 45)
      - American Institute for Research Plans: Survey, July 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 46)
      - Issue Poll Data, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 47)
      - Issue Poll Research, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 48)
      - Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 49)
    - Ephemera
      - Ephemera, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 22)
        - Know Your Next Congressman! Dick Thornburgh, 1966; 1.
        - Dick Thornburgh will stir things up in Congress, 1966; 2.
        - Pittsburgh needs Thornburgh in Congress because... Thornburgh works for Pittsburgh!, 1966; 3.
        - Are You Going to Vote for Dick Thornburgh?, 1966; 4.
        - If you are as concerned about FOOD PRICES as..., 1966; 5.
      - Ephemera, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Campaign Mailings
      - Pittsburgh Letterheads, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 24)
      - Pittsburgh Letterheads, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 25)
      - Addresses for campaign mailings, form letters, correspondence, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 26)
      - GOP Mailings, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Issues and position papers, 2.
    Thornburgh delivered twelve position papers on topics of concern to voters. In addition to the issued papers, and drafts, there are binders and folders of research materials designed for debate preparation and issue discussions. Several more folders were added to this subseries in July 2013.
    - Issue References (published materials) (annotated); some with historical material pre 1966 (Box 23, Folder 1-3)
    - Position papers (bound copy), November, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Position Paper #1: Help for the Aged, October 10, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Position Paper #2: We Need Better Law Enforcement, October 13, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Position Paper #3: Pittsburgh Can Solve its Transportation Problems, October 18, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Position Paper #4: A Better Way for Urban Renewal, October 20, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Position Paper #5: Education: Top Priority, October 24, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Position Paper #6: Vietnam as a Subject for Concern and Debate, October 28, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Position Paper #7: Civil Rights, October 30, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Position Paper #8: International Trade: When it Helps, When it Hurts, October 31, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Position Paper #9: Problems of Foreign Policy, November 1, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Position Paper #10: Economic Problems, November 2, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Position Paper #11: Poverty Programs Should Help the Poor, Not the Politicians, November 3, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Position Paper #12: Labor Problems, November 4, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Political and legal newsletters regarding the Thornburgh campaign, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Research Binder: Issues (annotated), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 18-19)
    - Research Plans, Drafts and Memos, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Question and Answer Session (annotated), August 27, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Neighborhood Youth Corps (annotated), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Moorhead Debate, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - The League of Women Voters Questionnaire (annotated), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Scranton/Shafer Administration Accomplishments, September 7, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - [New Material Added]
      - Urban Renewal and Housing, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 12)
      - Mainland China, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 13)
      - Labor Management, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 14)
      - Economy, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 15)
      - Europe Foreign Policy, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 16)
      - Education, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 17)
      - Health Care, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 18)
      - Water Pollution, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 19)
      - Poverty, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 20)
      - Foreign Policy, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 21)
      - Foreign Policy: South America, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 22)
      - International Trade/Balance of Payments, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 23)
      - Aging, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 24)
  - Opposition research, 3.
    Thornburgh's team carefully researched the various candidates for Congress, including their campaign materials, particularly about Thornburgh's general election opponent, William Moorhead. Several more folders were added to this subseries in July 2013.
    - Miscellaneous Candidates, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - William Moorhead Opposition Research (annotated), 1966-1969 (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - "Your Senator's Report," Transcripts of radio broadcasts with Senators Hugh Scott (R) and Joseph Clark (D), March, 1965-October,1966 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - Voters Guides, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - [New Material Added]
      - Housing/Urban Renewal, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 25)
      - Banking, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 26)
      - Taxation, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 27)
      - Public Health, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 28)
      - Defense, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 29)
      - Foreign Policy, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 30)
      - War on Poverty, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 31)
      - Education, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 32)
      - Mass Transit, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 33)
      - Voting Record Compared, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 34)
      - Disarmament, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 35)
      - Firearms, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 36)
      - Conservation, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 37)
      - National Humanities Foundation, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 38)
      - Civil Rights, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 39)
      - Labor Management, 1966 (Box 1010, Folder 40)
  - News releases and media, 4.
    These items are arranged chronologically and cover the dates February 12, 1966 - November 7, 1966. These reflect campaign debates, personal appearances and endorsements and are available here online. The media files relate both to the Thornburgh campaign efforts to gain media coverage as well as collections of newspaper clippings regarding the campaign.
    - Media Campaign (annotated), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - News Releases (annotated), February 12, 1966-October 18, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 31)
      - Thornburgh announces candidacy for Congress, February, 12, 1966; 1.
      - Oakland GOP for Thornburgh, February 26, 1966; 2.
      - GOP backing 100% for Thornburgh: Chairman hits Moorhead's record, February, 1966; 3.
      - Huge Thornburgh petitions lost and found, March 25, 1966; 4.
      - 14th District GOP rally set for Wednesday, April 11, 1966; 5.
      - Address of Thornburgh, candidate for Republican nomination for U.S. Congress in the 14th Congressional District at North Side Carnegie Music Hall\, Pittsburgh, April 13, 1966; 6.
      - Thornburgh urges democrat-GOP action at 14th Congressional District kick-off rally, April, 1966; 7.
      - Thornburgh hits Moorhead on failure to act for city youth, April, 1966; 8.
      - The Young Republican College Council of Allegheny County voted to endorse the candidacy of Thornburgh for Congress in the 14th Congressional District, April, 1966; 9.
      - Thornburgh endorsed for Congress by Senator Hugh Scott, May 10, 1966; 10.
      - Excerpts from remarks of Thornburgh before Civitan Club at downtown YMCA, Pittsburgh, June 20, 1966; 11.
      - Thornburgh says "More money for potato research than for cities", June, 1966; 12.
      - Thornburgh to attend 1966 Republican Candidates Conference, June, 1966; 13.
      - Thornburgh sees progressive look in '66 House candidates, 1966; 14.
      - Thornburgh-Moorhead debates scheduled for fall, 1966; 15.
      - Thornburgh charges Moorhead seeks "free ride" on legislation, 1966; 16.
      - Thornburgh calls for disclosure of all candidates' finances, 1966; 17.
      - Thornburgh questions Congressman Moorhead's willingness to debate, 1966; 18.
      - Thornburgh blasts Moorhead "buck passing" on proposed tax legislation, 1966; 19.
      - Thornburgh gets no reply to debate questions, August 2, 1966; 20.
      - Thornburgh charges administration "squeeze" on young home buyer, August 4, 1966; 21.
      - Thornburgh criticized Administration policies which have produced record high consumer prices and home mortgage interest rates, August 10, 1966; 22.
      - Youth for Thornburgh give 10th ward Republican headquarters new face, August 12, 1966; 23.
      - Thornburgh scores Moorhead for House absenteeism, August 16, 1966; 24.
      - Thornburgh charges Moorhead with "turnabout" on tax increase, August 17, 1966; 25.
      - Thornburgh questions Moorhead's concern about poverty, August 21, 1966; 26.
      - Statement of Thornburgh, Republican Candidate for United States Congress 14th Congressional District of Pennsylvania calling for disclosure of personal finances of candidates, August 24, 1966; 27.
      - Thornburgh calls for Moorhead to disclose finances, August 26, 1966; 28.
      - Thornburgh to address Republican women, September 7, 1966; 29.
      - Thornburgh headquarters opening announced, September 8, 1966; 30.
      - Philadelphia District Attorney to campaign for Thornburgh and Markovitz, September 9, 1966; 31.
      - Heinz and Rust to head Thornburgh campaign, September 9, 1966; 32.
      - Thornburgh opens headquarters in Oakland, September 16, 1966; 33.
      - Thornburgh announces plans for position papers, September 18, 1966; 34.
      - Thornburgh calls for election spending reform law, September 20, 1966; 35.
      - Thornburgh blasts Moorhead stand on "Big Ditch", September 23, 1966; 36.
      - Thornburgh calls for investigation of President's Club, September 27, 1966; 37.
      - Thornburgh charges opponent and city with neglect in renewal projects, September 27, 1966; 38.
      - Thornburgh demands FBI probe of Pittsburgh numbers racket, September 30, 1966; 39.
      - Thornburgh says safety director can release police survey on time, October 1, 1966; 40.
      - Thornburgh says FBI investigating Pittsburgh gambling, October 2, 1966; 41.
      - Thornburgh urges release of police survey to assist FBI and state police probes, October 4, 1966; 42.
      - Thornburgh proposes statue to Kirwan in place of Billion-Dollar Ditch, October 6, 1966; 43.
      - Thornburgh said that Moorhead is not vigorously opposing the Billion-Dollar Ditch project, October 8, 1966; 44.
      - Thornburgh issues 7-point position paper on aged, October 10, 1966; 45.
      - Thornburgh position paper proposes measures to fight crime, protect innocent, October 13, 1966; 46.
      - Thornburgh sends President Johnson recommendations to improve Pittsburgh transit, October 16, 1966; 47.
      - Thornburgh says city, county transit problems worsen because of 'footdragging', October 18, 1966; 48.
    - News Releases, October 20, 1966 - 1967 (Box 23, Folder 32)
      - Senator Scott to campaign with Dick Thornburgh on Friday, October, 1966; 1.
      - Thornburgh warns against driving people into poverty ghettos; supports urban renewal housing, October 20, 1966; 2.
      - Thornburgh hits Moorhead on anti-red vote, October 20, 1966; 3.
      - Thornburgh chides Johnson administration efforts to cut education appropriations, October 24, 1966; 4.
      - Itinerary of Thornburgh, Republican candidate for Congress, 14th District, October, 1966; 5.
      - Thornburgh supports LBJ search for Vietnam peace but hits objection to criticism, unplanned policies, October 28, 1966; 6.
      - Thornburgh hits extremists for hampering rights, October 30, 1966; 7.
      - Thornburgh's remarks on civil rights, October, 1966; 8.
      - Thornburgh expressed concern over trade inroads of foreign cartels, October 31, 1966; 9.
      - Thornburgh hits opponent for United Arab Republic votes, November 1, 1966; 10.
      - Thornburgh faces Moorhead on "peculiar" vote record, November 1, 1966; 11.
      - Thornburgh says Moorhead votes enabled United Arab Republic to get $37 million of U.S. aid, November 2, 1966; 12.
      - Thornburgh says opponent's votes drive up food prices, November 2, 1966; 13.
      - Thornburgh supports anti-poverty efforts, hits those who deprive poor of funds, November 3, 1966; 14.
      - Thornburgh starts 'brochure blitz' of Pittsburgh supermarkets, November 3, 1966; 15.
      - Thornburgh says government, business not doing enough on chronic unemployment, November 4, 1966; 16.
      - Thornburgh, accompanied by Governor Scranton, called on Pittsburgh housewives to "boycott your Congressman", November 6, 1966; 17.
      - Thornburgh winds up campaign on prices, United Arab Republic, position papers, November 7, 1966; 18.
    - News Releases (bound copy), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 33)
    - Campaign Clips (annotated), 1965-1967 (Box 23, Folder 34)
  - Campaign volunteer effort, 5.
    Materials include individual volunteer instructional materials as well as extensive information reflecting the entire volunteer effort. Ginny Thornburgh was primarily responsible for this grassroots support and the files include her volunteer records and the binders that she created to track volunteer activities throughout the Fourteenth District. One of the sad moments associated with the campaign was a fire at campaign headquarters in the wee hours of the morning after Election Day. In the pouring rain the Thornburghs rushed there especially to rescue the volunteer files, only to find the gutter awash with their invaluable 3"x 5" cards.
    - Ginny Thornburgh Campaign File, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Ginny Thornburgh Door-to-Door Canvass File, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Door-to-Door Canvassing, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Sample Canvass Kit for Area Chairmen, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Volunteer Instructions, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Campaign Volunteers, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Binder: 14th Congressional District Door-to-Door Canvass Chairmen and Volunteers: Areas I-XV, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Binder: 14th Congressional District Door-to-Door Canvass Chairmen and Volunteers: Areas XVI-XXX, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Thornburgh's files, 6.
    These consist of items that Thornburgh kept close at hand during the campaign, and include his campaign and speech notes, and personal campaign files. As is typical for him, much of this material is handwritten and/or annotated and reflects his thinking as well as his actions as candidate.
    - Campaign Notes (annotated), 1966 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Thornburgh's Personal Congressional Campaign File: notes, strategy and issue research (annotated), 1966 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Thornburgh's General Congressional Campaign File: notes, issue research, correspondence and ephemera (annotated), 1966 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Speech and annotated Speech Notes, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Election results, 7.